<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    
    <title>Helge J. Zöllner, PhD</title>
    
    
    <description>Latest update on my research</description>
    
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Comparison of linear combination modeling strategies for GABA-edited MRS at 3T</title>
        <description>
          
          Our new preprint is out! We evaluated different modeling strategies for linear combination modeling of GABA-edited MRS at 3T. Parameterizing the co-edited macromolecules at 3-ppm improved overall fitting performance. Different modeling strategies were tested: combining six approaches to account for co-edited MMs, three modeling ranges, three baseline knot spacings, and using basis sets with and without homocarnosine. Significantly different GABA+ and GABA estimates were found when a well-parameterized MM basis function at 3 ppm was included. The mean GABA estimates were significantly lower when modeling MM, while CVs remained similar. Sparser knot spacing led to lower variation in the GABA...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2021-05-27-Preprint-editedLCM-05/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021-05-27-Preprint-editedLCM-05/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SpecVis v.1.0.0 Release</title>
        <description>
          
          

I’m happy to announce the release of SpecVis v.1.0.0 today. This R repository includes a number of functions to create reproducible and information rich plots for transparent data reporting.

The functions are freely avaialbe on the SpecVis GitHub.

If you have any suggestions please contact me,

        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 16:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2021-05-08-SpecVis-Release-04/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021-05-08-SpecVis-Release-04/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MRSinMRS markdown in Osprey</title>
        <description>
          
          Dear MRS community, we are happy to announce a new module in Osprey that automatically creates a table following the consensus recommendations. The output format is markdown which allows opening in any text editor independently of your OS. The final document can easily be used to generate a PDF to attach for publication. Hopefully, this easy and open implementation allows other developers to join us and make this a standard output of any MRS analysis software. This could be very helpful to further increase the standardization and transparency of MRS studies. The new module will be included in the next...
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2021-04-26-Osprey-Updates-03/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021-04-26-Osprey-Updates-03/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inital post</title>
        <description>
          
          Hi!

I’ll use this blog to include announce new changes to Osprey and SpecVis as well as recent updates iabout my research.

Helge

        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 18:18:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/2021-02-20-Osprey-Updates-02/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2021-02-20-Osprey-Updates-02/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
